Preliminary Inventory of the Makerere University Slides, 1969
Hoover Institution Archives
- TANZANIA
  - SET III. THE CHURCH GROWS TO MATURITY.
    - This second map shews Catholic missionary extension by 1914, with Holy Ghost Fathers in the north-east, White Fathers in the West, and the Benedictines in the south-east. A number of other congregations have entered Tanzania since., T30.
    - The first African Catholic priests were ordained in 1917, and Msgr Willibald Mupaapi, seen in this picture, is still alive and active, and gets around Kashozi Parish (Buhaya) on a motorcycle. Tanzania has a larger number number of African priests than either Kenya or Uganda, though not nearly enough for her needs (there were 400 in 1969)., T31.
    - The years between the two World Wars saw almost all missions begin to train African clergy. The Lutherans, many of whom were Germans, and were sent back to Germany after World War I, perhaps saw the necessity for this most clearly, and when allowed back, ordained a number of men who had already proved themselves as leaders. Here is Pastor Aburahamu Mdoe Itunda, born in 1890 in Pare, baptised in 1909, though he had already worked for the Lutherans as ateacher since 1907. He continued to work as a teacher, and was ordained in 1934, working mainly in Gonja Pastorate. He retired in 1957, having completed 50 years of work for the Lutheran Church., T32.
    - This picture shews Tosamaganga, near Iringa in the Southern Highlands. A mission was first established here by the Benedictines in 1902, but when they were temporarily repartriated to Germany, part of their former territory was handed over to the Italian Consolata Fathers. Tosamaganga is now a huge parish centre with a hospital, several schools, including a secondary school, and both African and missionary sisters are at work there., T33.
    - The leadership of all Christian groups in Tanzania is now largely in African hands. This picture shews the Anglican Bishop of Dar es Salaam, The Right Rev. John Sepeku, blessing a new church for the Mission to Sea Men (The Archdeacon of Dar es Salaam is seen with him)., T34.
    - A church on a new housing estate in Dar es Salaam. Here, as in so many other urban areas, the churches face a new challenge. Missions were often originally placed well outside what was eventually to become a town centred around an old government administrative centre. As towns have grown, new sites have had to be bought and churches erected to meet the needs of urban dwellers. Church workers, both ordained and lay, have had to be trained to work in the new environment., T35.
    - His Eminence Cardinal Rugambwa is here seen with Pope John XXIII. Cardinal Rugambwa was the first African Cardinal. He was born in 1912, and ordained priest in 1943. In 1952 he was consecrated bishop, and was made Cardinal in 1960., T36.